A Guide to the Papers of the Smiley Family 1750-1959
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Smiley Family 1750-1959
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1807, -a
This collection consists of 390 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Smiley Family Papers were a gift to the Library from Mrs. Richard Hogshead of Staunton, Virginia, and Mr. Bowman Cutter of Waterford, Virginia, on December 13, 1943, and August 4, 1982.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of 390 items, 1750, 1772, 1778, 1827-1934, 1959, chiefly correspondence and financial and legal papers of the Smiley Family of Moffat's Creek, Augusta County, Virginia, but includes some of related families such as Hogshead, Earheart, Fulton, and other. Most of the correspondence pertains to Thomas M. Smiley, a Confederate soldier in Company D, 5th Virginia Regiment, First Division (the "Stonewall Brigade"). Topics discussed in his correspondence include: Confederate camp and civilian life; battles and campaigns such as First Bull Run, the Romney Campaign, Corinth, Yorktown, Cedar Mountain, Castleman's Ferry, and Chancellorsville; Thomas "Stonewall" Jackson, Turner Ashby, John Daniel Imboden, D. H. Hill, and Gustave T. Beauregard; Union atrocities; and the execution of a group of men of the 3rd Regiment, North Carolina, for desertion. Smiley was captured during the Spotsylvania Campaign of 1864 and was imprisioned at Fort Delaware, Delaware, and a few of his letters refer to his imprisionment. Post-war papers of Smiley relate to his business activities, reunions of the 5th Virginia and the 28th New York State Volunteers. There is a letter to him from Daniel Lamont, private secretary to Grover Cleveland, as well as a carte-de-visite, possibly of Smiley.
The collection contains miscellaneous correspondence including a 1772 letter from John Ralston, Lancaster, Pennsylvania, to his wife; an 1853 letter of John D. Imboden; references to Libby Prison, Castle Thunder (prison), and the treatment of prisoners of war; the Hampton Roads Conference, life at the Augusta Female Institute (later Mary Baldwin College), references to the Rev. Ebenezer D. Junkin and various family matters. Much of the financial and business papers pertains to William Smiley's lands in Randolph County, West Virginia, as well as property in Virginia. Included are a sight draft for John Imboden; papers pertaining to Texas land; a ledger/copybook regarding the construction and management of the Brownsburg Academy, Rockbridge County, Virginia; 1750 map possibly of Smiley land on Moffat's Creek; and 1772 and 1833 indentures. Other items include newclippings, a notebook of Mary A. Smiley, and electrostatic copies of transcripts from William Smiley Papers in the Archives and Manuscripts department of the State Historical Society of Wisconsin.
Contents List
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of Smiley and Hogshead families 1778, 1853-1865, 1879, 1938 & 1941, 9 items
- Correspondence of Thomas M. Smiley with related items 1858-1897 & 1903, 88 items
- Correspondence of Letitia Smiley, with related papers while attending Augusta Female Seminary 1864-1967, 13 items
- Smiley Family Family Financial and Legal Papers 1750, 1839-1898, 1919, 1920-1925, 125 items
  chiefly re William Smiley
- Financial and Legal papers 1827-1910, 64 items
  chiefly of William Smiley re land in West Virginia
- Financial and Legal papers of the Earheart, Fulton, Hogshead and other families 1829, 1853-1934, 1959, 52 items
- Ledger/copybook 1849-1880, 1 item
  re Brownsburg Academy, Rockbridge County, Virginia
- Notebook of Mary A. Smiley 1965-1866, 1 item
- William Smiley papers from The State Historical Society of Wisconsin 1840-1868, 26 items
- Miscellaneous 1884, n.d., 7 items
- Indenture between John Agnes Keys and Walter Smiley 1772 Nov 1, 1 item
- Indenture between Brown and Laura Jenks and George Smiley 1833 Aug 21, 1 item
- Plat of Hogshead, Lucas and Talley land 1917 Mar 8, 1 item
- Fire Insurance Policy of Miss L.R. Smiley and T.M. Smiley's heirs 1924 Jan 14, 1 item